Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 42: The Cycle of Kings (Awədä Nägäśət), Collection of Divination Texts, 1788-1800; 42; 126 folios 1 col. [fols. 1-30, 117-126]; 2 columns [fols. 31-116]; lines vary throughout. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two miniatures. Leather carrying case wi
  - Anqäs Concerning the Loss of Property or Money, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 15v. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Conflicts, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 15v-16r. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Messages and Appropriate Messengers, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 16r. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning How to Find Property or Money, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 16rv. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Having or Not Having a Child, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 16v. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Sickness, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 16v-17r. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning the Loss of Property or Money, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 17r. (Unitid 42)
  - The Numerical Value of the Letters of the Ge'ez Alphabet, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 17v. (Unitid 42)
  - Hasabä Səns Concerning the Fetus, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 17v. (Unitid 42)
  - A Reading from Psalm 121 [in Ethiopic Bible, Psalm 120], 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 17v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer of Moses, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 18r. (Unitid 42)
  - Reading from a Gospel, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 18r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer against Enemies, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 18v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for the Whole Year, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 19rv. (Unitid 42)
  - Astrology (On the Stars), 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 20r-44v. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of the Spirit (Hatäta Mänafəsət), 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 45r-71r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Tana, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 45r-47r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Kora, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 47r-48v. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Ela, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 48v-51v. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Zəway, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 51v-55r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Wənəg, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 55r-58v. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Daha, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 58v-60r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Hayəq, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 60r-62r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Heno, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 62r-64r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Šämazəbe, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 64r-66v. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Gəmb, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 66v-68r. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Täkäze, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 68r-69v. (Unitid 42)
  - Scheme of Lake Abawi, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 69v-71v. (Unitid 42)
  - Hasab Concerning Taking a Wife, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 71v-72r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for Getting a Gift, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 72r-72v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer With a Talismanic Symbol, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 72v-73r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer (In Arabic With Ge'ez Characters) With Magical Charts, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 73r-74r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer against Bleeding and Sickness During Pregnancy, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 74v-75r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Charts, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 75rv. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for Gaining Respect and Favor, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 75v-76r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer against Miscarriage, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 76v-77r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for Love, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 77r. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of Ezra, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 77r. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of Egypt, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 77r-78v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for a Safe Journey, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 78v-79v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for Gaining Respect and Favor, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 5v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for the Binding of a Slave, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 79vr. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for the Banishment of Demons, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 80r-81v. (Unitid 42)
  - The Numerical Values of the Letters of the Ge'ez Alphabet on a Separate Tiny Quire, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 82r-85v. (Unitid 42)
  - Calculation of the Copts, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 86r-88v. (Unitid 42)
  - Concerning the Best Dates to Go to War, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 88v. (Unitid 42)
  - Calendar of the Seasons, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 89rv. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer of Jeremiah, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 89v-90v. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of Aristotle, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 90v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prescription against Sickness, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 91r-92v. (Unitid 42)
  - Mästam (The Drowning), 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 93v-98v. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of Enoch, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 98v-99r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prescription against Various Diseases, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 99r-100r. (Unitid 42)
  - Hasab, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 100r-101r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer for Protection When Herding Animals, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 101r-102r. (Unitid 42)
  - Net of Solomon, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 102r-105r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayers, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 105v-108v. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Charts in Ge'ez and Magical Prayers Written in Arabic With Ge'ez Letters, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 109r-111v. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of Egypt, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 112rv. (Unitid 42)
  - Computation of Daniel, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 112v-116r. (Unitid 42)
  - Ge'ez Verbs, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 116. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prescription against Diseases, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 117r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayers and Hasab of the Children of Jesse, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 117r. (Unitid 42)
  - Lists of Possibilities, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 118r-121v. (Unitid 42)
  - Hasab of the Circle of the Year, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 122rv. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prescription against Diseases, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 122v-124v. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Sickness, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 124v-125v. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Love, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 125v. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning the Loss of Property or Money, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 125v-126r. (Unitid 42)
  - Anqäs Concerning Daily Subsistence, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 126r. (Unitid 42)
  - Magical Prayer against Chest Pain, 1788-1800; multiple folios; Located on folio 126rv. (Unitid 42)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 43: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam) and Miracles of Saint George (Tä'amərä Giyorgis), 1700s; 43; 77 folios 2 cols. [fols. 1r-67v], 19 lines; 3 columns [fols. 68r-77v]), 21 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. No wooden boards, leather cover, stitched and covered spine. 21 x 27 cm (Unitid 43)
  Fols. 5r, 6v, 8r: States "Commissioned by Sofənəyos Akəlidewos".
  Large Arabic numbers added much later in pencil on bottom of folios.
  Fols. 58r, 67v: In the Miracle of Mary text, the name of the owner/benefactor is listed as Särsä Micha'el.
  Fols. 68r, 73v: In the Miracle of Saint George text, the name of the owner/benefactor is listed as Bəsə'a Giyorəgis.
  Fol. 58r: A note in another, later hand is the beginning of a letter draft, that says "Letter sent from Bishop Mattewos, archbishop of the kingdom of Ethiopia, servant and apostle of Christ, the son of Saint Mark." Mattewos was bishop from 1889 to 1926.
  Owner: Särsä Micha'el, Bəsə'a Giyorəgis.
  References: See references in manuscript no. 8. Regarding Miracles of Saint George, see Victor Arras, Miraculorum S. Georgii Megalomartyris collection altera, Louvain 1953 (CSCO 138,139); Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 2, pp. 763-764.
  - Miracles of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-67v. (Unitid 43)
    - First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1rv. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Barok, a dissolute man (incomplete) (Budge, Mary, 26; Strelcyn 32.16.26).
    - Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa (Incomplete At the Beginning), 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r-4v. (Unitid 43)
    - Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 4v-6v. (Unitid 43)
    - Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 6v-8r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anəsətasəyos) (Budge, Mary, 27; Strelcyn 32.16.27).
    - Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 8rv. (Unitid 43)
    - Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 8v-9v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the Jew of Akəmim, an elderly priest, when he fell and broke his back during his service in her church (incomplete at the ending, folio missing) (Budge, Mary, 03).
    - Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 10r-11r. (Unitid 43)
      How Marəqos, King of Rome, fled from his palace for the monastery for the love of the Virgin Mary.
    - Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 11r-12r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the dying monk in the island of Tigris.
    - Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 12r-13r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to the widow and commanded her to recite the "Hail Mary" (Budge, Mary, ?).
    - Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 13rv. (Unitid 43)
    - Tenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 13v-14v. (Unitid 43)
    - Eleventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 14v-15v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain woman on the altar of the monastery.
    - Twelfth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 15v-17r. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 17r-18v. (Unitid 43)
    - Fourteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 18v-20r. (Unitid 43)
      How the icon of the Virgin Mary in a certain church bowed to the young person who served in the church and when he bowed to her (Budge, Mary, 104, for a different version).
    - Fifteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 20v-21v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary saved from death a governor of Eferan named Armatəyas.
    - Sixteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 21v-22v. (Unitid 43)
    - Seventeenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 22v-23v. (Unitid 43)
    - Eighteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 23v-25r. (Unitid 43)
    - Nineteenth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 25r-26r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twentieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 26r-27v. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 27v-29r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 29r-30r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared out of her picture to Mary, the daughter of a certain God-fearing man from Dafra, to give her communion and promised to take her to Paradise after three days (Budge, Mary, 7).
    - Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 30rv. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary carried a sick person from the Monastery of the Pilgrims to Jerusalem and showed him where Jesus was crucified and buried and baptized him in the waters of the Jordan) (Budge, Mary, 9; Strelcyn 32.16.9).
    - Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 30v-32v. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 32v-33r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 33r-34v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary saved two Muslims from the storm when they called on her name (Budge, Mary, 12; Strelcyn 32.16. 12).
    - Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 34v-36r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the eyes of Yohannəs Bäkänəsi, the blind priest in Egypt, by anointing him with milk from her breasts (Budge, Mary, 14; Strelcyn 32.16.14).
    - Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 36r-37r. (Unitid 43)
    - Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 37r-38v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary restored the sight of Elizabeth, a blind girl, with her breath and milk (Budge, Mary, 16; Strelcyn 32.16. 16).
    - Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 38v-39r. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 39r-40r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed the foot of a widow from Harətärom) (Budge, Mary, 24).
    - Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 40r-43r. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 43r-44v. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 44v-45r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary healed Bishop Märqorəwos of his leprosy (Budge, Mary, 23; Strelcyn 32.16.23).
    - Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 45r-46v. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 46v-49v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary aided in the delivery of a child to an abbess before the bishop came to enquire into the matter (Budge, Mary, 25; Strelcyn 32.16.25).
    - Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 49v-50v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary cut out and sewed a garment for Filatawos, a bishop of the city of Sä'id in Upper Egypt (Budge, Mary,40).
    - Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 50v-51v. (Unitid 43)
    - Thirty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 51v-52v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary moved the Monastery of Ekona (Budge, Mary, 13; Strelcyn 32.16. 13).
    - Fortieth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 52v-53v. (Unitid 43)
      How Abba Samu'el levitated from the ground and spewed fire from his mouth and was not touched by the rain when he read the praises of the Virgin Mary (not in Budge).
    - Forty-First Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 53v-55v. (Unitid 43)
    - Forty-Second Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 55v-57r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary and Jesus and the Angels came to Pifamon before his martyrdom (not in Budge).
    - Forty-Third Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 57r-58r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary helped a Roman prefect when a mysterious ram prevented him from visiting Christ's tomb until he had become a follower of the Virgin Mary (Budge, Mary, 39).
    - Forty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 58r-61r. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary rebuked a woman who gave up fasting at her husband's command (Budge, Mary, 99).
    - Forty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 61rv. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary delivered from prison a certain man called Giyorgis (Budge, Mary, 19; Strelcyn 32.16. 19).
    - Forty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 61v-62v. (Unitid 43)
      How the Virgin Mary protected the elderly priest called Qätir from the church door keeper by paralyzing the keeper (Budge, Mary, 20; Strelcyn 32.16. 20).
    - Forty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 62v-63v. (Unitid 43)
    - Forty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 63v-65r. (Unitid 43)
      How a certain rich man hurled a loaf at the head of a beggar and wounded him, and how the Virgin Mary delivered his soul from the devils) (Budge, Mary, 86).
    - Forty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 65r-67v. (Unitid 43)
  - Miracles of Saint George, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 68r-77r. (Unitid 43)
    - First Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 68r. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis appeared to Awəlogis and gave him a ship full of riches (incomplete at the beginning, see 75r-77v for the beginning).
    - Second Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 68r-71v. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis removed a priest from his ministry who had stolen a gift from the church and how he saved the priest from his sins.
      Second Miracle of Saint George is in a different hand.
    - Third Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 71v-73v. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis appeared as a builder to help the construction of the church in Ləda during the reign of Constantine.
    - Fourth Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 73v-75r. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis punished Awyan, the commander of Dəyoqəltyanos, when he destroyed the Church of St George in Jerusalem.
    - Fifth Miracle of Saint George, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 75r-77v. (Unitid 43)
      How Saint Giyorgis appeared to Awəlogis and gave him a ship full of riches (incomplete at the end, see 68r for the end of the miracle).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 44: Synaxarium (Lives of the Saints). Sənksar, early 19th century; 44; 228 folios 3 cols., 33 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards bound in stamped red leather, covered spine. Fols. 2rv, 228rv: Blank. Fols. 65rv: Quarter folio 24 x 32 cm (Unitid 44)
  Fol. 1r: Arabic numbers "2146," "183"; illegible Amharic words in pencil.
  Fol. 1v: Note of ownership in later hand in colored pencil "This synaxarium belongs to Däbrä Qədusan." Followed by two lines in Amharic in the same hand: "any person who reads this or listens may become a righteous person. The scribe is Aläqqa Esäy."
  At the end of every daily entry, the name Wäldä Micha'el appears in the original text.
  Owner: Wäldä Micha'el.
  No scribe listed in original manuscript.
  References: Regarding the Ethiopic Synaxarium, see Conti Rossini, Manoscritti ed opere abissinein Europa, Rendiconti della Reale Accademia dei Lincei, vol. Viii, 1889, p.630. H.Zotenberg, Catalogue des manuscrits éthiopiens (gheez et amharique de la Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris 1877. No.126 and 128,pp.152-95; S. Grébaut et E. Tisserant, Codices aethiopici Vaticani et Borgiaani Barberinianus Orientalis 2, Rossianus 865, Città del Vaticano, (1935-36) No. 111 -112; Strelcyn.(B.M). 54; EMML 4273; 4274.
  - Sənksar (Synaxarium for the Second Half of the Year), early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-227v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Mäggabit, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-38v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Miyazya, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 39r-65v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Gənbot, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 66r-104r. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Säne, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 104r-140v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Hamle, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 141r-186v. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Nähase, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 186v-221r. (Unitid 44)
    - Entries for Pagwame, early 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 221v-227v. (Unitid 44)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 45: Synaxarium (Lives of the Saints). Sənksar, circa 1730-1899; 45; 226 folios 3 cols., varies due to repairs, but mostly 34 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards missing, parchment cover, stitched and open spine. fols. 1r, 35v, 103v, 192v: Blank. Some folios were quarter or half folios. The top right quarter of almost all folios (1v-192v) appears to have been damaged, seemingly by fire. It was repaired by cutting away those sections from each folio and sewing new pieces in. The new portions are in another hand. Sometimes the scribes had to squeeze text to make it fit. The repairs were probably done in the late 1800s. 33 x 38.5 cm (Unitid 45)
  Fol. 225v: Ge'ez alphabet with Ethiopic numbers.
  Fol. 226r: Ge'ez alphabet in pencil.
  Fol. 226v: Pen trial.
  At the end of every daily entry appear the names of the manuscript owners / benefactors Wäldä Häwarəyat and Fasilädäs.
  Fol. 1v: In another hand, that of the sewn-in-portions of the folios, is a scribal note: "Praise to God, the Lord of Michael [the Archangel], who enabled us to finish this book without weariness or exhaustion, without sickness or distress, with joy and peace. The scribe of this book is Gəra Geta [church title] Hayəlu Hayəlä Micha'el with his son Gəra Geta Därsäh Gäbrä Həywät. Do not forget us in your prayers."
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 44.
  - Sənksar (Synaxarium for the First Half of the Year), circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r-225vv. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Mäskäräm, circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r-35r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Təqəmt, circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 36r-66r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Hədar, circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 67r-103r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Tahəśaś, circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 104r-145v. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Tərr, circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 146r-192r. (Unitid 45)
    - Entries for Yäkkatit, circa 1730-1899; multiple folios; Located on folio 193r-225v. (Unitid 45)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 46: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), late 17th century; 46; 166 folios 3 cols., 27 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. One wooden board covered in stamped leather, stitched and open spine, lower board missing. Cloth on inside cover. Fol. 1r: Erased, upside down six-line note. Folio is not part of quire, but a folded single piece of parchment. Fols. 2rv, 8v, 32v: Blank. fol. 166v: The last miracle is incomplete, at least one folio is missing 30 x 32.5 cm (Unitid 46)
  Fol. 125r: The "King of Ethiopia" is mentioned, but not his name.
  Most of the miracles in this manuscript take place in Egyptian monasteries.